<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on SoftWhat?</title>
    <link>https://softwhat.com/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on SoftWhat?</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© 2016-2020 Alex Pulver</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://softwhat.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Automated Path From Hardcoded SQL Queries to SQLAlchemy ORM With Flask</title>
      <link>https://softwhat.com/automated-path-from-hardcoded-sql-queries-to-sqlalchemy-orm-with-flask/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://softwhat.com/automated-path-from-hardcoded-sql-queries-to-sqlalchemy-orm-with-flask/</guid>
      <description>Let&amp;rsquo;s assume you started by developing the database schema directly on the server (e.g. using MySQL Workbench) and used hardcoded SQL queries in the code (e.g. using one of Transaction Script, Domain Model or Logic in SQL approaches).
Then at some point you feel confident to use SQLAlchemy&amp;lsquo;s Object-Relational Mapping (ORM) framework. On a side note, I highly recommend to read OrmHate article by Martin Fowler to get some perspective on when to use ORM frameworks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drilling Down to Amazon EC2 Instances Data Transfer Costs</title>
      <link>https://softwhat.com/drilling-down-to-amazon-ec2-instances-data-transfer-costs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://softwhat.com/drilling-down-to-amazon-ec2-instances-data-transfer-costs/</guid>
      <description>The use case I would like to address in this post revolves around the need to understand which specific Amazon EC2 instances incur the highest data transfer charges, including high-level understanding of traffic flow (e.g. to/from Internet, inter-region, intra-region and etc.). For detailed analysis of traffic flow, I would recommend to use Amazon VPC Flow Logs – see Querying Amazon VPC Flow Logs in Amazon Athena (serverless query service) documentation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bootstrapping Tcl Unit Testing With Tcltest</title>
      <link>https://softwhat.com/bootstrapping-tcl-unit-testing-with-tcltest/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://softwhat.com/bootstrapping-tcl-unit-testing-with-tcltest/</guid>
      <description>If you are working with Tcl, and interested in adding unit tests to your project using tcltest, read on.
Usually there is some bootstrap work required to run your unit tests. For example, every test should load the relevant libraries before using them in a test. There is also a need in a test runner that would execute the test suite and report results. Since there are several ways to implement the above, and there are some gotchas along the way, I thought it would be useful to provide a reference implementation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Couchbase Python SDK on Cloud Foundry</title>
      <link>https://softwhat.com/using-couchbase-python-sdk-on-cloud-foundry/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://softwhat.com/using-couchbase-python-sdk-on-cloud-foundry/</guid>
      <description>I wanted to use Couchbase as a session store for my app instances, and specifically Couchbase Python SDK. The problem I faced was that Couchbase Python SDK (and some of Couchbase other non-C SDKs) requires Couchbase C SDK to be installed a priori – it is not installed by pip automatically.
Sadly, Conda package manager doesn’t have Couchbase C SDK in its repository, so I could not use Cloud Foundry Python Conda buildpack to install it (it can be very useful to install SciPy for example, which is supported by Conda).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>